Benjamin B. Odell Letters
Benjamin B. Odell Letters
1901-1922
Odell, Benjamin B. (Benjamin Barker), 1854-1926.
9 items (SC)
Papers of the New York State Governor, 1901-1904. Both incoming and outgoing correspondence, three items of which concern the selection of Ray Brook as the proposed site of the State Hospital for consumptives. Correspondence with Horatio Collins King, Anson G. McCook, John G. McCullough, Nathan L. Miller, Henry Codman Potter, and others.
149341
Biographical History
Benjamin Barker Odell was an American politician who served as the Governor of New York from 1901 to 1904.
Odell was born on January 14, 1854 in Newburgh, New York to Benjamin Barker Odell, Sr. and Ophelia (Bookstaver) Odell. He attended Bethany College in West Virginia before transferring to Columbia College. After his junior year at Columbia, Odell returned home to join his father's ice business. Odell started as a driver of the ice wagon, but eventually became the head of the company. In 1877, he married Estell Cristee who tragically died in 1888 when she drowned in the Hudson River.
Around 1884, Odell was selected as a member of the Republican State Committee and in 1895 was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives. Serving two terms, Odell acted as chairman of the Committee on Accounts during his second term. In 1891, he was remarried to Linda Traphagen, the widowed sister of his first wife. Most markedly, Odell served as Governor of the New York from 1901-1904.
Throughout his lifetime, Odell also held positions as the Ice Controller of the State during World War I, President of the Consolidated Gas, Electric Light, Heat, and Power Company of Newburgh, and President of the Hudson Steamboat Company. He died on May 9, 1926 in Newburgh, New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Benjamin B. Odell Letters consist of nine items written between 1901 and 1922.
Two of the incoming letters (A. G. Mills, Henry Codman Potter) protest the selection of Ray Brook (near Lake Placid) as the proposed site of the State Hospital for consumptives. An outgoing letter refers another item on the same subject to Timothy L. Woodruff's attention.
Four of the letters offer recommendations to the then Governor for appointments to State agencies. Letters from Wilson S. Bissell and John Griffith McCullough recommend the reappointment of Ashley W. Cole to the State Board of Railroad Commissioners. An item from Nathan L. Miller suggests the appointment of William Crane of Homer for the Board of Visitors to the Binghamton State Hospital.
A letter from Horatio Collins King requests a meeting on behalf of Judge Michael H. Hirschberg.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains one series, Correspondence, which is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has several collections that contain correspondence to and from Benjamin B. Odell. The Chauncey M. Depew Letters contain one piece of correspondence to Odell, while the Elihu Root Correspondence contains one piece of correspondence from Odell. The Horace White Papers contain correspondence both to and from Odell. Please contact the Repository listed above for more information on these materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; King, Horatio C. (Horatio Collins), 1837-1918.; McCook, Anson G. (Anson George), 1835-1917.; McCullough, J. G. (John Griffith), 1835-1915.; Miller, Nathan L., 1868-1953.; Odell, Benjamin B. (Benjamin Barker), 1854-1926.; Potter, Henry Codman, 1834-1908.; Governors -- New York (State); Tuberculosis -- Hospitals -- New York (State); Tuberculosis -- Hospitals -- Public opinion.; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; New York (State) -- Officials and employees -- Selection and appointment.; Correspondence.; Governors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Bissell, Wilson Shannon, 26 Dec 1902; 1 incoming typescript letter (Sc 42)
  - King, Horatio Collins, 29 Apr 1904; 1 incoming holograph letter (Sc 42)
  - McCook, Anson G., 21 May 1901; 1 incoming holograph letter (Sc 42)
  - McCullough, John Griffith, 14 Feb 1902; 1 incoming typescript letter (Sc 42)
  - Miller, Nathan Lewis, 24 Feb 1902; 1 incoming typescript letter (Sc 42)
  - Mills, A. G., 22 Mar 1901; 1 incoming typescript letter (Sc 42)
  - Potter, Henry Codman, 22 Mar 1901; 1 incoming typescript letter (Sc 42)
  - Snyder, Edward Havemeyer, 05 Jan 1922; 1 outgoing typescript letter (Sc 42)
  - Woodruff, Timothy Lester, 02 Apr 1901; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 42)